# **GAURAV SOOD**

#### Sr. Data Scientist



**J** +91 9632714987

Bangalore, India

github.com/gsood-gaurav



"Senior Data Scientist with 7 years of experience in Data Science and total experience of 14 years in software industry, contributed as an individual contributor and team leader, building machine learning models from conception to completion to improve operational efficiency. Worked on Natural Language Processing, Time Series Forecasting, Tabular Datasets. Experienced in traditional machine learning methods (Probabilistic Graphical Models), deep learning models (LSTMs, CNNs), Transformer based models (BERT, GPT and LLMs), Graph Neural Networks and Reinforcement Learning"

#### SKILLS

Python     PyTorch     TensorFlow     JAX     Julia     Flux/Lux     NumPy     SciPy     Matplotlib
Large Language Models         Generative AI         Probabilistic Modelling         Reinforcement Learning         Time Series Forecasting
Communication Leadership Skills

### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Sr. Data Scientist

#### HP Inc. May 2021 - Ongoing

- **B**angalore, India
- Created Large Language Models(LLMs) Based application for webpage content filtering and topic recommendation, adhering to key NFRs which helped in acheiving Net Promoter Score of 65 during beta testing of HP's PrintAl program
- Benchmarked LLM based application's performance on accuracy, cost(token usage) and latency, comparing OpenAl, Llama and Mistral, reducing cost by 30%.
- Mentored **3** data science interns on automated triaging using Graph Neural Networks and LLMs, completed within an expedited time frame of **2 months**
- Supervised Small Language Models(SLMs, less than **3B** parameters, **4bit** quantized) exploration and **instruction fine-tuning** initatives using PEFT acheiving an accuracy of **95**%
- Created Telemetery data analysis pipline processing 0.5 million customer record using LLM embeddings, BERT, dimensionality reduction(UMAP, Variational AutoEncoder) and clustering HDBScan, enhancing operational efficiency by 20%-30%.

Prompt Engineering (GPT2) TinyLlama (FineTuning) Embedding Models) Graph Nerual Netwo	Prompt Engineering	Embedding Models Graph N	erual Networks
---	--------------------	--------------------------	----------------

## Sr. Software Engineer Machine Learning

#### HP Inc. July 2017 - May 2021

- **B**angalore, India
- Analyzed the effects of key macro economic indicators on long and short term forecasts of product sales data which
  helped in acheiving on-time delivery rate of 90-95%, working with HP's Digital Transformation Office across US and
  Brazil
- Implemented Hyperparameter Tuning module for Time Series models using Optuna reducing the AutoML framework execution time by 20%-25%
- Worked on HP Personal Systems User Behavior Modelling using Tree Based Models, SHAP, UMAP, HDBScan for targeted market campaigning
- Developed simulator environment for online Reinforcement Learning for automated hardware diagnostics, as an alternative to Sequence Based Modelling
- Mentored 4 interns on Sequence Tagging Models using BERT, LSTMs, Conditional Random Fields for discovering insights in call center records which lead to 25%-30% increase in operational efficiency.

- Presented and communicated ideas about Probabilistic Modelling and Reinforcement Learning to senior leadership
- Analyzed 0.1 million call center record using Bayesian Networks for predictive diagnostics as an aid to call center executives and evaluate their decision making process

Time Series Analysis CART Reinforcement Learning Probabilistic Graphical Models Data Annotation

#### Senior Software Engineer

HP Inc. March 2015 - June 2017

- **B**angalore, India
- Created a parser for PostScript Language to extract images and meta data which was impacting **50000** hp customers and saving **\$0.5** million
- Worked on understanding PDF specification, design and implemented PDF document processing using PDF libraries like iText and PDFium which helped in saving annual licensing cost of \$10,000
- Lead a team of 4 software engineers which delivered imaging processing solutions using Python Imaging Library, Tessaract OCR to over 10 Public sector banks across India

 $\left( \mathsf{Algorithms} \right) \left( \mathsf{OpenSource\ Sofware} \right) \left( \mathsf{Image\ Processing} \right) \left( \mathsf{Leadership\ Skills} \right)$ 

### Software Engineer

HP Inc. May 2010 - Feb 2015

- **B**angalore, India
- Designed and Implemented Telemetry module in python using asyncio which enabled the collection of data across 1 millon devices used by hp customers
- Collabrated with **7** software engineers on open source software used by **1** million customers worldwide (https://developers. hp.com/hp-linux-imaging-and-printing)

Python Open Source Software Asynchronous Programming

## PREVENTIVE DISCLOSURES

- Gaurav Sood, Ranjith Kumar Gopa, Nandan Kumar Nidhi(May 2024) "Representing Tabular Data using Large Lanugage Models" https://www.tdcommons.org/dpubs\_series/6998/
- Gaurav Sood (Feb 2021) "A Reinforcement Learning Approach to Printer Diagnostics" https://www.tdcommons.org/dpubs\_series/4244/
- Gaurav Sood, Pavleen Kaur Brar, Raghu Anantharangachar (April 2019) "Sequence Prediction for Print/Scan Issues using Bayesian Networks" https://www.tdcommons.org/dpubs\_series/2117/

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

Deep Learning Specialization

Coursera Oct-2021 Credential ID G8PG2GY6WFS)

Reinforcement Learning Specialization

Coursera Sept-2021 Credential IDD3LDNU8BRW68

Introduction to Quantum Computing

Coursera May-2021 Credential ID RXQHLEC2WYC8

## **EDUCATION**

MSc Research Speech Recognition Indian Institute of Science Bangalore 2006-2009

• E Speech Recognition using Support Vector Machines